Guide to the Carolyn Burke Collection on Mina Loy and Lee Miller
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Carolyn Burke Collection on Mina Loy and Lee Miller
1904-2008
1976-2005
YCAL MSS 778
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.8
(21 boxes)
The Carolyn Burke Collection on Mina Loy and Lee Miller consists of Carolyn Burke's research files, correspondence, writings, and original documents pertaining to Mina Loy and Lee Miller. These original documents were obtained by Burke during the course of her research, primarily from Loy's daughter, Joella Haweis Bayer, and Miller's son, Anthony Penrose. The 2011 acquisition includes the bulk of the collection's Mina Loy papers. This acquisition includes autograph manuscripts and fragments of writings, including the prose pieces "Alda's Beauty" and "Promised Land." Correspondence by Mina Loy and family members is especially well represented, and family photographs and records of Loy's inventions are also present. The 2012 acquisition contains 14 audiocassettes, transcripts, and notes from Burke's interviews in the late 1970s and 1980s with Loy's daughter, Joella Haweis Bayer. The 2013 acquisition includes further autograph manuscripts by Loy. Manuscript fragments for Loy's "Colossus," "Psycho-Democracy," and other poems are present in this acquisition, as is correspondence, photographs, and a small amount of business records. The bulk of the 2013 acquisition, however, is Burke's research files for the Loy and Miller biographies. Original documents pertaining to Lee Miller are present in this acquisition and include a small amount of correspondence and family photographs. These items have not been separated, and are noted at the file level.
Burke, Carolyn
Arrangement
Organized into three groupings: December 2011 Acquisition, January 2012 Acquisition, and July 2013 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time. Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 18, 19, and 20 (audiocassettes and VHS cassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 21 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Related Materials
Mina Loy Papers (YCAL MSS 6). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Carolyn Burke
Carolyn Burke is a biographer, art critic, and academic. She was born in Sydney, Australia and has taught in American and Australian universities, including the University of California Santa Cruz, Princeton University, the University of California Davis, the University of Western Sydney, and New South Wales University. Burke has written biographies of Mina Loy, Lee Miller, and Edith Piaf. In the course of writing biographies for Loy and Miller, Burke compiled research files comprising both original documents from her subjects, as well as her research work.
Mina Loy
Mina Loy (1882-1966) was a modernist poet whose work expanded technical boundaries and concerned oppression of women, and a playwright, actress, and designer.
Lee Miller
Lee Miller (1907-1977) was a war correspondent during the Second World War, and a photographer and fashion model.
Scope and Contents
The Carolyn Burke Collection on Mina Loy and Lee Miller consists of Carolyn Burke's research files, correspondence, writings, and original documents pertaining to Mina Loy and Lee Miller. These original documents were obtained by Burke during the course of her research, primarily from Loy's daughter, Joella Haweis Bayer, and Miller's son, Anthony Penrose.
The 2011 acquisition includes the bulk of the collection's Mina Loy papers. This acquisition includes original manuscripts and fragments of various writings, including the prose pieces Alda's Beauty and Promised Land. Correspondence by Mina Loy and family members is especially well represented, and family photographs and records of Loy's inventions are also present.
The 2012 acquisition contains 14 audiocassettes, transcripts, and notes from Burke's interviews with Loy's daughter, Joella Haweis Bayer.
The 2013 acquisition includes further original documents by Loy. Manuscript fragments for Loy's Colossus, Psycho-Democracy, and other poems are present in this acquisition, as is correspondence, photographs, and a small amount of business records. The bulk of the 2013 acquisition, however, is Burke's research files for the Loy and Miller biographies. Original documents pertaining to Lee Miller are present in this acquisition and include a small amount of correspondence and family photographs. These items have not been separated, and are noted at the file level. Audiovisual material from the 2013 acquisition has been separated to the Audiovisual Material series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Thomas A. Goldwasser Rare Books, Inc. on the Adele Gutman Nathan Theatrical Collection Fund, 2011. Gift of Carolyn Burke, 2012. Purchased from Thomas A. Goldwasser Rare Books, Inc. on the Alfred Z. Baker, Jr. Fund, 2013.
Poetry, Modern -- 20th Century; Futurism (Literary movement); Futurism (Art); Surrealism (Literature) -- France; Biographers; Poets, English -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States; Photographers -- United States; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Biographies (documents); Sound recordings; Biographers; Poets, English -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographers -- United States -- 20th Century; Burke, Carolyn; Loy, Mina; Miller, Lee, 1907-1977
- December 2011 Acquisition, 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Organized under three headings: Writings, Correspondence, and Other Papers.
  Scope and Contents
  The December 2011 acquisition includes Mina Loy papers from the collection of Carolyn Burke, including manuscripts and fragments of various writings, such as Alda's Beauty and Promised Land. Correspondence of Mina Loy and associated family members, family photographs, and records of Loy's inventions are also present in the acquisition.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from Thomas A. Goldwasser Rare Books, Inc. on the Adele Gutman Nathan Theatrical Collection Fund, 2011.
  - Writings
    - Alda's Beauty, autograph manuscript, 1916-1916 (Box 1)
    - Promised Land, autograph manuscript, 1937-1937
  - Correspondence
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Bayer, Joella to Mina Loy and Fabienne Loy, 1917-1948
    - Bayer, Joella to Mina Loy, 1926-1936
    - Defries, Amelia to Stephen Haweis, circa 1912-1913
    - Defries, Amelia to Stephen Haweis, with research notes by Carolyn Burke, circa 1912-1913
    - Harter, Ethel, circa 1933-1934
    - Levy, Julien and Edgar to Joella Bayer, 1951-1956, 1967
    - Levy, Julien to Mina Loy, 1927-1929
    - Lloyd, Fabienne to Mina Loy and Joella Bayer, circa 1935-1942
    - Loy, Mina to Joella Bayer and assorted others, circa 1934-1949, 1960
    - General correspondence, 1912-1959
  - Other Papers
    - Papers relating to Mina Loy's inventions, 1940, 1946
- January 2012 Acquisition, 0.83; (2 boxes)
  The January 2012 acquisition consists of 14 audiocassettes, transcripts, and notes from Carolyn Burke's interviews with Mina Loy's daughter, Joella Haweis Bayer.
  Gift of Carolyn Burke, 2012.
  - Interviews with Joella Bayer
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 19: Use of original audiocassettes is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Audiocassette tapes, 1978-1981, 1989 (Box 19)
    - Notes from Joella Bayer, 1979-1991 (Box 2)
    - Notes by Carolyn Burke, 1978-1981, 1989
    - Transcripts, 1978-1981, 1989
- July 2013 Acquisition, 7.5; (18 boxes)
  This portion of the collection is organized into four series: Mina Loy Papers, Carolyn Burke Research Files on Mina Loy, Carolyn Burke Research Files on Lee Miller, and Audiovisual Material.
  The July 2013 acquisition contains original documents by Mina Loy and Lee Miller. Manuscript fragments for Loy's Colossus, Psycho-Democracy, and other poems are present in this acquisition, as is correspondence, photographs, and a small volume of business records. The bulk of the acquisition, however, consists of Carolyn Burke's research files for the Loy and Miller biographies. Original documents pertaining to Lee Miller are included in the research files and include a small amount of correspondence and family photographs. These items have not been separated, and are noted at the file level.
  Purchased from Thomas A. Goldwasser Rare Books, Inc. on the Alfred Z. Baker, Jr. Fund, 2013.
  - Mina Loy Papers
    - Writings
      - Also this ivy, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 3)
      - Colossus, autograph manuscript fragments, undated
      - Psycho-Democracy, autograph manuscript fragment, 1919-1919
      - Repassed Platform, typescript, undated
      - Unidentified typescript by Loy and Andre Germain about Arthur Craven, torn in half, circa 1920s
    - Correspondence
      - Family, 1911-1949
      - Family, Aspen, 1958-1965
      - Grandjean, Nelly to Arthur Craven and Mina Loy, circa 1911-1912
      - Lindsay, Robert, circa 1957
      - Loy, Mina to Joella Bayer and Julien Levy, circa 1950-1954
    - Other Papers
      - Photographs, circa 1905-1988
      - Business Files, 1929, undated
  - Carolyn Burke Research Files on Mina Loy
    This series contains Carolyn Burke's research files compiled in the course of researching and writing her biography of Mina Loy, Becoming Modern. Folder titles were taken from those supplied by Burke, and folders have been left in the order in which they arrived at the library.
    The research files typically contain Burke's notes and duplications of original material. Any original documents pertaining to Mina Loy have been noted at the folder level.
    Audiovisual material from Burke's research on Mina Loy has been separated to the Audiovisual Material series.
    - Abbott, Bernice: Letter and interview, 1978-1978 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence regarding David Mann show, 1959-1959
    - Aspen to Denver, 1977, 1988
    - Guggenheim, Peggy, undated
    - Vail, Lawrence and Sinbad, 1968, 1985
    - Bunting, Basil, 1978, 1980, 1998
    - Cornell, Joseph, 1979, 1980
    - Independents and Louis Eilshemius, 1917, 1979
    - London: Women artists, undated
    - Art school, London: General documents, undated
    - London 1982 notes, bibliography, and research, 1980, 1982
    - Duchamp and New York Dada, 1980-1987
    - Art schools, fashions, and Royal Academy, circa 1980-1999
    - English art scene in the 1890s and 1914, 1980-1980
    - Mensendieck, 1987-1987
    - London: Girls' education from 1880 to 1900, 1984-1984
    - Bodley Gallery invitation, 1959-1959
    - Haweis family, 1967, undated
    - Jews, undated
    - London streets, geography, and Mina Loy's houses, 1982-1982
    - The Peep of Day, undated
    - 1880-1900 London: General social history, 1981, undated
    - Haweis, Stephen and Rodin, 1987, 1990
    - Haweis, Stephen: Columbia research, undated (Box 5)
    - Haweis, Stephen: Chronology, 1991, 1993
    - Stieglitz, Alfred and Camera Work: Aphorisms on Futurism, undated
    - Manuscript poems in 1940s, undated
    - Contact Collection of Contemporary Writers (1925) and Anglo-Mongrels and the Rose II, undated
    - Lunar Baedecker (1923), undated
    - International Psycho-Democracy (1918-1919), undated
    - Loy, Mina: Modern Poetry, Charm (1925), undated
    - Male mods. [?] regarding Marianne Moore and Mina Loy, undated
    - Trend, undated
    - Burke, Carolyn: Rediscovering Mina Loy, 1979-1979
    - Burke, Carolyn: Mina Loy for The Gender of Modernism, 1989-1989
    - Burke, Carolyn: Virginia Woolf and Mina Loy text and notes, undated
    - Beinecke records, 1977-1990
    - International, undated
    - Kreymborg, Alfred and Others, undated
    - Others, undated
    - New Age, undated
    - Charm, undated
    - Little Review, undated
    - Transatlantic Review, undated
    - Contact, undated
    - Playboy, undated
    - Bouche, Louis and Belmaison, undated
    - Barnes, Djuna in New York from 1915-1917, undated
    - 1920s: Poetry, New Age, Dial, undated
    - Loy, Mina in The Evening Sun, 1917-1917
    - Loy, Mina: Addresses, 1977, undated
    - Loy, Mina: Chronologies from 1920s to 1935, undated
    - Baker, Elizabeth for Art in America on Frances Simpson Stevens, 1991-1993
    - Stevens, Frances Simpson, 1980-1992
    - Dial and Scofield Thayer, undated (Box 6)
    - Evening Sun (Winter 1916-1917), undated
    - New York 1915: Reviews of Mina Loy and others, undated
    - Varise, Louise Norton: Interview, 1982-1982
    - Wood, Beatrice, 1978, 1998
    - Salon d'Automne, Gazette des Beaux-Arts, 1904-1923
    - Blind Man and O Marcel, undated
    - Oelze, Richard, 1991, undated
    - Merton, Thomas, undated
    - Christian Science research and Mina Loy, 1990-1990
    - Barnes, Djuna: Letters, undated
    - de Gramont, Elisabeth and Carol Guddal, 1988-1988
    - Poesie-Peinture, undated
    - Barnes, Djuna in Paris: Texts, undated
    - Bibliotheque Doucet and Natalie Barney, 1977-1977
    - Barney, Natalie, circa 1920, undated
    - David, Hermine, undated
    - Bryher, Winifred, 1962-1962
    - Pascin, Jules, undated
    - McAlman, Robert on Mina Loy, undated
    - Pound, Ezra: Paris, undated
    - Man Ray and Mina Loy, 1989-1989
    - Wyndham, Lewis and The Starry Sky, undated
    - Paris in the 1920s, circa 1978
    - Joyce, James and Ulysses, undated
    - Wilde, Oscar, undated
    - Brancusi, Constantin ( Brancusi's Golden Bird ), undated
    - New York Evening Sun (1916), undated
    - New York Evening Sun and Don Marquis (1915-1916), undated
    - Loy, Mina: Exhibition at Julien Levy Gallery (1933) photographs and reviews, undated
    - Brown, Susan: Correspondence regarding Mina Loy and Jaded Flowers, 1978-1978
    - Paris: Mina Loy's bottle collection, 1972-1972
    - Loy, Mina: Lampshades, undated
    - Laughlin, James: Letters from Mina Loy, circa 1950, 1990
      This folder contains one autograph manuscript letter from Mina Loy to James Laughlin, as well as photocopies of letters.
    - Levy, Julien, 1932, 1977-1981
    - Aziz and Nimet, undated (Box 7)
    - Loy, Mina: Lamps photographs, circa 1920, undated
    - Loy, Mina: Paintings and constructions, undated
    - Laughlin, James: Correspondence, 1979, 1990
    - Loy, Mina: Literary correspondence from Aspen, 1981, undated
      Folder includes two autograph manuscript letters by Mina Loy; one is to Djuna Barnes. Folder also contains copies of letters to Loy from the researcher James Mechem and from her friend Robert Vas Dias and a letter from the curator of the Poetry/Rare Books Collection at the State University of New York at Buffalo to Carolyn Burke.
    - Bayer, Joella: Letter and drawing of Costa San Giorgio, 1980-1980
    - Williams, Jonathan: Correspondence, 1958, 1969, undated
      Folder includes one autograph manuscript letter from Mina Loy to Jonathan Williams, with photocopies of other letters.
    - Loy, Mina: Correspondence from the Bowery (1949-1954), undated
    - Creeley, Robert: Correspondence, 1980-1980
    - Nicholson, Nigel: Correspondence, 1982-1982
    - Bowles, Paul: Correspondence, 1981-1981
    - Grosser, Maurice: Correspondence, 1981-1981
    - Marinetti, Luce: Correspondence, 1985-1985
    - Levy, Julien: Correspondence, 1976, 1978
    - Cody, Morrill: Correspondence, 1978-1978
    - Roditi, Edouard: Correspondence, 1976-1976
    - Johnson, Diane: Correspondence, undated
    - Josephson, Matthew: Correspondence, 1977-1977
    - Wood, Beatrice: Correspondence, 1978-1978
    - Bunting, Basil: Correspondence, 1980-1980
    - Killian, Kevin: Correspondence, 1987-1989
    - Boyle, Kay: Correspondence, 1976-1978
    - Thompson, Virgil: Correspondence, 1976-1976
    - Bayer, Joella: Correspondence, 1976-1991
    - Benedict, Fabienne [Fabienne Lloyd]: Correspondence and interviews, 1976-1993
    - Willis, Patricia: Correspondence and notes on Mina Loy and Marianne Moore, 1988-1993
    - Fraser, Kathleen: Correspondence, 1991-1993
    - Ostriker, Alicia: Correspondence, 1993, undated
    - Conover, Robert: Correspondence, 1981-1996
    - Fitch, Noel Riley: Correspondence, 1978-1985
    - Rexroth, Kenneth: Interview notes, 1977-1977
    - Paris interviews: Virgil Thompson, Charles Henri Ford, and others, 1977, 1982
    - Burke, Carolyn: Correspondence, 1976-1979
    - Januzzi, Marisa: Correspondence, 1991-1994
    - Sawelson-Gorse, Naomi: Correspondence, 1986-1991
    - Hartigan, Lynda: Correspondence, 1979-1995
    - Naumann, Francis: Correspondence, 1978-1979, 1989
    - de Lanux, Eyre: Correspondence, 1979-1979
    - Kouidis, Margaret: Correspondence, 1989-1991
    - Josephson, Matthew: Correspondence and interview, 1978, undated
    - Lynes, George Platt, 1991, undated
    - Watson, Steven: Correspondence, 1989-1992
    - Burke, Carolyn: Correspondence to be refiled, 1977-1997 (Box 8)
    - Philadelphia: Arensberg Collection and New York, 1979-1986
    - Levy, Julien to Mina Loy, circa 1959
      Folder includes three typed letters, signed, from Julien Levy to Mina Loy, and photocopies of other letters.
    - Levy, Julien and Joella Bayer: Marriage certificate, 1977-1977
    - Mason, Audrey (Bryan): Correspondence, 1978-1989
    - Bayer, Joella: Family legal documents, 1927, undated
    - Lowy family birth certificates and Sigmund Lowy will, 1977-1989
    - Loy, Mina: Records, documents, and addresses, undated
    - Loy, Mina: Rue du Colisee boutique, 1977-1977
    - Interviews, 1977-1982
    - Thompson, Virgil: Interviews, 1977-1977
    - Williams, William Carlos, 1979-1979
    - Jacobs, Roz: "Christ on a clothesline" interview, 1989-1989
    - Laughlin, Clarence John: Correspondence and interview, 1981-1993
    - Sproat, Elaine and Lola Ridge: Correspondence, 1977-1978
    - Archives and research letters, 1978-1989
    - Bayer, Javan and Jerrola Levy, 1982-1989
    - Vas Dias, Robert: Correspondence regarding Paul Blackburn Mina Loy tape, 1980-1993
    - Loy, Mina: Drawings and photographs, 1987, undated
    - New Yorker with Carolyn Burke's translation of Arthur Craven, 1997-1997
    - Roche, Juliette, 1977-1977
    - Loy, Mina: Galleries and painting, undated
    - Mina and Colossus: A New Musical, 1998-1998
      Includes audio CD and programs for Mina & Colossus: A New Musical
    - Boffin, Hilda: Correspondence, 1999-2000
    - Logue, Antonia, 1999-1999
    - Beach, Sylvia: Archives at Firestone Library, undated
    - Rosenbach: Marianne Moore correspondence, undated
    - Craig, Gordon and Martin Shaw, 1981, 1988, undated (Box 9)
    - Lacerba, undated
    - Futuriste: Expo and chronology, 1986-1990
    - Futurism: Feminism, 1986-1990
    - Italia futurista notes, undated
    - Papini, Giovanni and Futurism in Florence, undated
    - Papini, Giovanni: Texts, undated
    - Herron, George D., undated
    - Sprovieri, Giuseppe: Interviews, 1985-1985
    - Cook, George: Mina Loy and Futurists (1914), undated
    - Burke, Carolyn: Correspondence, 1999-2004
    - Burke, Carolyn: Notes on Mina Loy's correspondence, undated
    - Julien Levy Gallery, 1933-1933
    - Beinecke Library: Finding aids and notes, 1987, undated
    - Le Savoureux, Madame Henri, 1977-1977
    - Becoming Modern, Notes and Related Papers
      - Outline, undated
      - Introduction: Notes and drafts, undated
      - Prologue: Notes and comments, 1992, undated
      - Chapter 1: The Bud Beside the Rose, 1993, undated
      - Chapter 1: Notes and fragments, undated
      - Chapter 2: Art School notes, undated
      - Chapter 3: Munich notes, 1911, undated
      - Chapter 4: Manuscript and notes, undated
      - Chapter 5: 1904-1909 notes and scraps, 1990, undated
      - Chapter 6: Notes, undated
      - Chapter 7: Notes, undated
      - Chapter 8: Gordon Craig in Florence, undated
      - Chapters 8-9: Florence chronology notes, undated
      - Chapter 8: 1913-1914 notes, undated
      - Chapter 9: 1914-1916 notes, undated
      - Chapter 10: Notes, 1980, undated
      - Interlude: N2, Brown talk, "Love songs", 1992-1992 (Box 10)
      - Chapter 11: Colossus notes, undated
      - Chapter 12: Notes, undated
      - Chapter 13: Notes, undated
      - Chapter 14: Notes, undated
      - Chapter 15: Notes, undated
      - Chapter 16: Being Geniuses notes, undated
      - Interlude II: Anglo-Mongrels notes, undated
      - Chapter 17: Notes, undated
      - Chapter 18: Notes, 1989, undated
      - Chapter 19: Stanton Street, 1977-1989
      - Chapter 20: Aspen interviews, 1978-1988
      - Stein, Gertrude (1911-1912, 1920s), undated
      - Bibliography: Chapters and places, undated
      - Flap copy and captions, undated
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, 4
      - Page proofs, undated; 4 (Box 11)
  - Carolyn Burke Research Files on Lee Miller
    This series contains Carolyn Burke's research files compiled in the course of researching and writing her biography of Lee Miller, Lee Miller: A Life. Folder titles were taken from those supplied by Burke, and folders have been left in the order in which they arrived at the library.
    The research files typically contain Burke's notes and duplications of original material. Any original documents pertaining to Lee Miller have been noted at the folder level.
    Audiovisual material from Burke's research on Lee Miller has been separated to the Audiovisual Material series.
    - Miller, Lee: Original documents, 1907-1966
      Includes family photographs, theater programs, newspaper clippings, and other documents, "from Theodore Miller diaries."
    - 1960s, 1966, undated
    - Library at FF [?], undated
    - Memorabilia, 1928, undated
    - Julien Levy Gallery exhibition, 1932-1932
    - Miller, Erik: Photographs, copies, 1933-1933
    - Withers, Audrey, 1997, undated
    - Chronologies, 2000-2000
    - Bibliographies, general, and models, undated
    - Bibliographic research, 1997-2000
    - Sontag, Susan: Regarding the Pain of Others, 2003-2003
    - Mayor Gallery, 1999-1999
    - Reviews of resources, 1990-1999
    - Sexually transmitted diseases, 1999-1999
    - Trauma, 1999-2002
    - Miller, Lee: Reproduced interviews, undated (Box 12)
    - Miller, Lee: Interview with Ona Munsen, 1946-1946
    - Critical studies of Lee Miller's photographs, 1999-1999
    - National Public Radio tapes, transcripts, 1989-1989
    - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) documentary, 2001-2001
    - Miller, Lee: Exhibition reviews, 1989-1990
    - Miller, Lee: Birth certificate, copy, 1965-1965
    - Miller, Florence, 2000, undated
    - Miller, Lee: Father/daughter relationship, 1997, undated
    - Miller, Lee and Man Ray: Solarization, undated
    - New York from 1926 to 1927, 1996, undated
    - Notes on Lee Miller's 1926-1927 diary, undated
    - Vassar, undated
    - Cornell, Joseph, 1978, 1999
    - Treillard, Lucien: Interviews, 1998-2000
    - Man Ray: Images, undated
    - Man Ray, 1998, undated
    - Victor Considerant apartment, 1999
    - Blood of a Poet, undated
    - Von Salta, Mary Anita Loos, 1999-1999
    - Blitz, undated
    - Steichen, Edward, 2000, undated
    - Kotex and early modeling of 1927-1928, undated
    - Women and Surrealism: Interview with Francine du Plessix Gray, 1996-1996
    - Frogue, 1998-1998
    - Hoyningen-Huene, George, undated